All right, welcome back to our uh first
ever AMR overtures discussion. My name
is Joel Sinclair and I'm a pastor in
Silver Spring, Maryland and an executive
board member of the Alliance for Mission
and Renewal. Uh the AMR cares deeply
about the PCA and we put in time and
energy to work toward or or foster a
unified and faithful PCA. And part of
how we're doing that today is through
having discussions uh with David Coffin,
Fred Greco, and Howy Dano about uh
overtures. That is uh an ask typically
from one of our 87 presbyaries uh to the
general assembly uh for an amendment uh
to our constitutional standards or to uh
take action uh do something different.
And today we're having our third
discussion uh on uh some of the
overtures that have been submitted for
this upcoming uh 52nd general assembly
in Chattanooga. Uh we are going to be
looking at in this third discussion uh a
handful of overtures and uh I'm going to
kind of clump them together. Maybe we
can talk about uh voting uh jurisdiction
and membership. So, some of the
overtures that touch on voting,
jurisdiction, membership, may maybe a
category of like process. Um, and so
we're going to be covering a number of
these uh with each of you having the
opportunity to weigh in. Thanks so much,
uh, for joining us. As we kick off, I I
want to make sure before we highlight
any of uh the overtures where there may
be disagreement or where we talk through
in the overtures themselves, which are
linked below, as well as the guides uh
that each of these men have written
independently where they share their
thought in detail, oftentimes with maybe
amendments that would make the overtures
better or uh reasons or rationale for
why they are voting in in one way or in
the other. There is uh quite a bit of
agreement in those guides which are
linked below. In fact, in overtures uh 6
7 10 11 13 14 15 16 19 22 23 25 27 28 31
32 33 35 37 and 40. They pretty much
recommend the same answer except
sometimes with varying reasons why. Um,
and so when we pick out a handful of
overures to talk about voting or
jurisdiction or membership or area
process that that there may be some
disagreement, I just want to recognize
that that comes uh really in the setting
of quite a bit of agreement. And so uh
let's uh pick it up together uh with
overture 7. Uh this is an overture that
comes from Missouri Presbyter and it's
uh really an overture to amend BCO341
which is known um uh by some as is kind
of the paragraph that oversees original
jurisdiction or the assumption of
original jurisdiction. Uh now in your
guides um I I'll note that uh for uh
Overture 7 uh Howie Dano recommended
voting in the negative on this. Fred
Greo recommended in the negative and
then David uh your answer I I don't want
to categorize it because unless I I mess
up and miscatategorize it. So would you
tell us what are your thoughts here
about Uber 7? Um well um
in 1879
this paragraph said process against the
minister shall be entered before the
presbyter of which he's a member.
Period.
And that strikes me as just the right
place and just the right amount of words
for this uh section.
Um the language that's there now was
added because of a case in the southern
church
where a very famous uh professor was um
becoming derelictked in his views. His
presbyter wouldn't do anything about it
and the PCA decided they wanted to do
something have something to do about it.
uh they lived with it only applying to
ministers until about 1988.
Uh in the first uh study committee that
I served on as a ruling elder, the uh
the committee on restructure,
uh somebody finally noticed that this
wasn't applicable to ruling elders in
chapter 33. And so we wrote a version of
it. In fact, we wrote a better version
of it than the one that's in 341.
Uh, and because it's different, it
caused a good bit of confusion. But in
any case, um, I I helped to do that. And
so I'm a guilty party here because I
think this is a very very bad provision.
And I'd like to see the the overtures
committee in fact just strike all of
that language. I think it's uh
illconsidered because
um
in chapter 40 there are remedies where
someone can bring something before the
assembly if they need be. uh and um if
there's no person in that presbyterary
that will act when there's some
dereliction with respect to another
minister, we have a much greater problem
than uh uh simply one person. Um but the
my main concern is there is no way to
have anything remotely akin to due
process or an evidentary standard.
It simply says if people say there's a
bad thing and a a number of them, a
relatively small number, and the
assembly can take a jurisdiction,
uh I I don't think this is a a proposal
that's likely at all to lead to justice
and I don't think it even has very much
usefulness in helping to protect the
presbyteries. And I think the
alternatives that we have are are just
and uh will perfectly accommodate what
is intended by these paragraphs in 33
and 34.
Thanks so much.
Uh Howie Fred, responses, thoughts,
anything you'd add?
Yeah. Um I've been trying to change this
paragraph for almost 20 years. Um
refuses to act is too vague. Uh two or
three presbyteries is too low. Um I
think I've tried unsuccessfully a couple
times. I think if we said change refuses
to act that declines to indict and bump
it up to 15 to 20% of the presbyteries,
uh it would pass and it would solve a
lot of problems.
When So is that what you mean? Can you
just clarify just for for me even uh two
to three presbyaries too low? Are are
you thinking when this was originally
written, the number of of protoaries
there were at that time? Uh, and that's
way too low. Okay. No, it's way too low.
I mean, if there's um I'll give you an
example. I mean, a couple years ago,
there was a high-profile case out of St.
Louis and the presbyterary declined to
indict. Uh, that was so high-profile it
it wouldn't have been hard for 15% of
the presbyteries to petition for
assumption of original jurisdiction. If
it's not a problem or if it is a big
problem, shouldn't be hard to get 15% of
the press returns and that would have
procedurally dealt with that thing a
whole lot easier.
Hey Fred, before I jump over to you, can
can I just ask Howie on the fly here? I
can imagine that there are some who
would say creating a higher bar creates
uh uh the need to um incite others to
act to uh share details to potentially
present one side of a case in order to
get a prespitary because hey we need
this 15 or 20%. So I just I I with the
use of social media today with with how
um I think of a unified and faithful PCA
as one that is operating with some level
of trust in our fellow pressers. Um can
you h how is that a concern if you jump
that bar up? What do you think about
that? Happy to respond to that because
what I would say is all that social
media stuff is going to happen anyway.
it did happen in the case I referenced
this at at at worst
would mitigate some of that. I mean,
people send an email to some friend in
another presbyter and say, "Hey, see if
you can get your presbyterary to
petition for AOJ, right?" Um, you don't
have to do that on social media. I mean,
it hopefully if it's done expeditiously,
it keeps stuff off of social media.
Yeah. AOJ being the assumption of
original jurisdiction there. Yeah.
Fred,
why don't we first thanks for just like
what I hear you saying is like some of
this it's it's it's baked in to the pie
of of American Presbyterianism already
certainly in the 21st century like it's
I mean if it's a if it's a doctrinal
matter or case of scandal it's on the
internet you can't stop it
unfortunately. Yeah. And and I think I'm
not as optimistic as how would be
because we tried last time together and
the PCA found a way to reject both of us
at the same time. we couldn't clear
twothirds of the presbyteries was where
it failed. That's a really high bar and
in doing that um and so you know there
was for example there was another
highish profile case at the exact same
time that the case was coming out of St.
Louis. People forget that there were
other requests for assumption of
original jurisdiction. And it may be
that the solution is what David has
suggested
um which is to use review and control
under 40-5. It's never been done before
in that exact vein, but that may that
may be the solution. Um, but I think
this uh overture needs to die a much
quicker death than ours did. Uh, because
I think not only will it not pass, if it
did pass, this isn't a good solution for
a number of reasons.
Okay, fair. Thank Thanks each of you.
Um, so moving on to overture 9. Overture
9 comes from James River. It is an
amendment um in in in in the categories
of like uh jurisdiction membership. This
would be under voting for overture
number nine uh an amendment to BCO41
uh on how the AC functions uh with
regard uh to votes. Um uh in in this uh
for overture 9 um Howie I'm going to ask
uh if you would kick us off here on a
conversation. What are your thoughts
about overture 9 and amending VCO14 and
impacting how AC how the voting process
goes there? Yeah, I I'll try to be
quick. I wrote kind of a lengthy
rationale in my recommendation that it
be answered the negative. So, I'll just
highlight
um four things. one. It was also
referred to all the permitting
committees and agency boards and eight
of the nine of them recommended
answering James River 9 in the negative.
M&A an recommended answering in the
affirmative but didn't give ground. So I
don't know what makes the difference but
um the second thing is I I think it's
like a lot of things probably some of
the things I actually have written it's
a solution in search of a problem
because to my knowledge I don't remember
and I've been to 33 gas I don't remember
a time when an committee of
commissioners on admin committee
recommended a substantially different
thing than the admin committee itself
which means
Uh the admin committee has been
functioning pretty well.
Um the third thing is if this passed it
would shrink the admin committee from 20
voting members to 11. And I think
that kind of centralizes power more than
diffuses it. And it's usually the
opposite of what we argue argue for. I
give you an example. There's
there's 11 members of the permanent
committee
other than the designates from the
agencies and boards
and one presetary has two men on the AC
committee. Two out of the 11.
And that presbyter
well there's 30 presbyteries in the PCA
that have more churches than that
presbyter. So, two guys in one
relatively smaller presbyterary with
voting positions on the AC. So, I mean,
I think it'd be a different overture if
it said uh disenfranchise the the
design, but bump the whole AC up to 20
or 30 members or something. So, I I
think it's a a bad idea to shrink it to
11.
Okay. And partly partly because the
design
um are men that were elected by the by
some a general assembly to be on that
permanent committee. So it's not like
the permanent committee found some guy.
They're all elected by the GA. Now they
weren't elected
necess they weren't elected to function
as an AC member. Their permanent
committee is the one that designated
them for that.
Still they were elected by the GA. So
thanks.
On this one I think
it it's helpful to be reminded of what I
take to be a fundamental principle and
that is with respect to any overture the
burden of proof is on the proposer.
They have the obligation to show that
there's a good reason for doing this.
And as far as I can see, there's no
evidence that the current scheme causes
any kinds of difficulties at all. They
certainly didn't propose in the
overture. And that in itself, I think,
is enough reason to vote against it.
Fred, uh, you have thoughts?
One main thought that I've had and I put
in my commentary is one of the reasons,
maybe the main reason all of the
permanent committees recommended against
it was that they wanted they didn't want
to lose their vote on their budgets
because the budgets are approved by the
administrative committee. And that
actually joged for me something. Uh, I'm
not sure why, for example, we're only
giving one MTW representative a vote out
of 20 on the large MTW budget. That
doesn't seem to make any sense at all to
me. Uh, I would like us to see uh I
would like to see us change that. I
don't see any reason why the MTW budget,
which is not unified with the other
budgets, couldn't come up through the
MTW committee commissioners. and the
same with M&A and the same with Geneva
and the same with the AC. It seems to me
that that would not really take up much
more time on the assembly floor. It
would infranchise the permanent
committees much more. Give them much
more say and control um than that. If I
were, you know, M&A, I wouldn't want one
out of 20 votes. I'd want 10 out of 10
votes or 12 out of 12 votes uh on my
budget.
Oh, it may actually save some time,
Fred, because we waste time every year
with people trying to figure out whether
we should pass Yes. budget during the
committee's time or whether it's waiting
until we get to AC. I usually is the
chairman of the committee of
commissioners doesn't know what to do.
Yeah, you're correct. You are correct.
Oh my. Yeah.
All right. Uh, thank you very much. Uh,
so that covers overture 7, overture
nine. Uh, so I'd like to move to
overture one. Uh, which is BCO. Uh, so
this is Northern New England uh,
submitted in overture number one. So
they got it in uh, closest to the last
general assembly. It gets it gets listed
in in order typically chronologically.
That's how these numbers get assigned.
Uh and so number one from Northern New
England to amend BCO 322 regarding
investigations. Now uh Fred and and
David both recommended votes in the
negative on this. How you vote it uh or
you recommend a vote in affirmative. So
I'm going to give you the the first dibs
here in terms of jumping in. Uh what do
you think about amending 322?
Well, it's an uphill climb because uh
I've been in many SJC discussions with
Fred and David on this issue and we
principally think differently. So, um I
think it it makes sense. Um it helps. We
have had cases that
um someone brings a charge against
someone else and um some people think,
well, the presbyperary has to adjudicate
that charge unless it's clearly
unsupported or it's from a 318 accuser
or something like that. Uh but normally
you have to adjudicate the charge. Um
I'm of the of the position that Matthew
18 says tell it to the church. But that
doesn't mean uh tell them when you're
going to appear as the prosecutor in
that case. is just tell it to the church
and let the church decide whether it's
an offense that warrants prosecution,
whether it's provable at trial, whether
it's, you know, merits the amount of
attention a presbyator would have to
give to it or a session. Um,
so I'm very much in favor of overture
one. Okay,
Fred. Well, this is where I'm old enough
to remember. I think the rest of you are
too. remember um Crossfire, the old CNN
show where they'd bring people on and
would, you know, argue back and forth.
This is probably one of your most argue.
It's interesting. You know, this is a mo
a point of procedure and this is
probably where at least Howie and I have
the greatest disagreement. As Howie
says, we've been fighting about this in
SJC cases for a while. Um and Howie
always brings up the are you going to,
you know, have a trial for an 8-year-old
who brings charges against his
10-year-old brother for hitting him? And
my answer is yes. and the trial will
last five minutes. Uh, and you go on.
Um, I I think this is a really bad idea.
Uh, I think it does away with voluntary
prosecutors. I think it it really has
the unintended effect of insulating
teaching elders from any lay person
because as soon as you enter into this
process of overture one, any lay person
loses standing to file a complaint if
the presbyterary declines to go forward.
I think that's a very bad look in our
modern age. Um I I just think it's
unnecessary. I've been preaching for
years that 312 and 322 are not
sequential. They are parallel. Uh and
that's the way the SJC has ruled, you
know, for many a time. So, um I'm I'm
respectfully but very is as as eager as
Howie is for it, I'm eager against it.
Can I just ask to clarify uh make sure
that I'm setting this up right for those
who are watching and aren't as familiar
as as the three of you with judicial
process. So if a a church or a
presbyterary were to go to trial,
there's often two routes to go to trial
in our book. One route would be if that
court does a 312 uh investigation based
on a report and determines a strong
presumption of guilt there to move to
trial. That would be one avenue to get
to a trial. That's one route that you
could take and like if you're looking on
Google Maps or ways and it gives you an
alternate route with the amount of time.
The other route would be if a person
including a lay person or someone not a
member of that court arrives to the
court with charges and said I am filing
charges against member X. Uh then you're
understanding if I'm reading this
correctly this overture would allow in
that instance to kick back over to route
one. something that Howie's in favor of
and and Fred, your concern is that if
you kick over to route one, that's going
to become always a de facto route and
route two will never be used and then
the net effect of that is the lay person
doesn't actually have access to the
court anymore versus right now they do
have that. I think that would be a
surprise because I think the average
person a doesn't see a lot of trials to
begin with and then b doesn't know that
people outside the court would have
access to do things like bring charges.
Is is that is everything that I just
said is that a fair summary? Would you
correct something that I've said or I
think so. I think so. And I would only
add one other thing. We don't see a lot
of 322 charges because 31
uh 9 exists.
In other words, if someone becomes a
voluntary prosecutor and they do it
frivolously or without a uh a probable
cause, they can be censured. So in the
main in the PCA, I would say 90 out of a
100 times, 95 out of 100 times, someone
who's upset with someone else files a
report and asks the court to do it on
their own because they don't want to
take the risk of being seen as as a
slander of the brethren. They don't want
to take the risk of of that under 319.
So this is not, in my opinion, a rampant
problem that needs to be fixed. We don't
have people running around willy-nilly
filing charges. As a matter of fact, if
you look at like the last 12
controversies we've had in the last 15
years or so. They're all 312
controversies, not 322 controversies.
Right. And it could be 319. It could
also just be people aren't familiar
enough with process to know and and so a
report is what just gets classified.
Right. Like like it could be for a
variety of reasons. I I the reason why I
say that, Fred, is is I don't think
people outside of our courts are
unfamiliar with the BCO have much
concern with 319 because they don't know
what that says. Um yeah, Howie. Yeah, I
think Fred brought up a legitimate
point. I think the the problem could be
solved in a simpler way, in a better
way. So if um Sally Jones
uh files an allegation against Reverend
uh John Doe and Presbyter decides for
for example if this overture pass
decides for whatever reason it doesn't
warrant um prosecution um she doesn't
have BCO standing to file a complaint
against that presery action. Uh, I think
the solution to that isn't
let her be a volunteer prosecutor just
because she wants to be. The solution is
grant standing to people who are
personally offended and make accusations
against ministers. Just grant them
standing.
That's what I would do.
The book doesn't allow that yet, but I
think that's the way to solve that
problem.
David, do you have any thoughts that you
want to weigh in? Uh we've heard from
Howy and Fred a bit. Well, um I I don't
think just as a u aside on How's last
point, I don't think you should change
the book of church order
uh in a way that raises a problem with
the anticipation that you could correct
it later by changing some other part. I
I I that doesn't sound like a good
strategy to me. But in any case, it
seems to me there are many things wrong
with this proposal and not simply the
loss of the bifurcation and 322 that is
currently present.
Um it seems to me that it is putting way
too much uh credit with on book of
church order 318.
Putting that into the mix. It's there
but it's relatively obscure. Um but if
if you go to that that section
um
how is it that um
the court's going to conclude that
somebody has one of those
characteristics. The only thing there
that has has any reference to due
process is one who is himself under
censure or process.
every other one, the court would
actually have to convict that person of
being in some way characteristic in that
way. And I I think that's terrible. I
mean, listen to the language again. Um
the if I can get to it here quickly. Uh
the you're you're about to read from BCO
I'm going to give you a second just and
then so people can follow. You're about
to read the language from BCO 31
uh sub paragraph 8, right? 38. Okay.
Great caution ought to be exercised in
receiving accusations from any person
who is known to indulge in a malignant
spirit toward the accused. How's the
court going to know that? They're going
to investigate it
and and charge him and convict him who
is not of good character. How's the
court going to know that? Here's the
only one that actually you could
conclude. He's under center of process.
Next, who is deeply interested in any
respect in the conviction of the
accused? But it sounds like you're
objecting to BCO 318. I I am objecting
to it. I'm especially objecting to it
now being put into the prerequisites
of every case, which it's not there.
It's somewhere else. To put it in here
is going to highlight it. And I think in
a way that is destructive. Would you
favor this if we just struck D? I'd be
more likely to favor it, but I still
think that there the problem that you
and Fred say you're arguing about, I
don't think is a problem
for this reason. Um the uh every court
has some uh plausible way in which uh
they have discretion with respect to a
case.
Now you're identifying that discretion
and in a way that is uh I think way be
going to cause way more problems than
it's ever going to solve.
Right now
we have had SJC cases where in fact
there's been an enumeration of elements
of discretion. So right now 312
we we think we know what it means right
now and it means something that seems to
me large is largely agreeable to you and
largely agreeable to Fred. But this new
thing is going to be language that
nobody knows how it's going to be
construed and in my judgment likely in a
way that's very damaging.
I would say that um we had an SJC case
this year that had a rare 12 to 12 vote.
If this paragraph was changed, it would
not have been a 12 to 12 vote. If this
isn't changed, the next one will be a 12
to 12 vote.
I I am a little more optimistic than
that, but Okay,
fair enough.
Um,
thanks to each of you for weighing in on
this. Um, and for sharing some backstory
of uh the Crossfire effect between Fred
and Howie that's been going on for years
that none of us none of us apparently
knew. Hey guys, it doesn't come out when
we see you hug at General Assembly. Who
would have known years and years of of
builtin uh 322 uh arguments happening
there? Listen, when we when we agree on
so much, we've got to have violent
disagreement about small provisions in
the rules of discipline.
Um, one of the things that one of the
things that would help in this
discussion,
and it wasn't in the whereas clauses,
and I'm not sure I even put much of it
in my rationale, is to come up with case
law, case scenarios, like how would Fred
and Howie deal with this differently.
And if we come up with six and we both
deal with them the same, then maybe
nothing's needed to be fixed.
And I think probably we could come up
with six that the three of us would
would agree on. So,
Um,
yeah, it's the to me it's mainly
uh
I would be mainly concerned with someone
who's alleging a personal offense and
alleging a personal offense allegedly
committed by a minister is the primary
thing I think
um on the table. I don't think
Um,
if someone makes an accusation that a
minister is
heretical and the presbyter looks at it
and go clearly he's not.
Um, certainly that that wouldn't be
prosecuted. So
I if I could just um
this seems to me to be a relatively
important point. Uh this is one of the
principles that I articulated for
thinking about overtures. There's a
general objection to any proposed change
in the book of church order. Any new
language will include undiscovered
ambiguities that might well have
disastrous unintended consequences.
consequences that will only appear when
the provisions are tested in cases by
sharp and contending minds seeking
possible meanings to their advantage.
Thus, unless the changed proposed is
clearly necessary, the older language is
to be preferred because it already has
been long tested in cases and persuasive
precedents guide the church as to its
meaning. This seems to me to be a case
in point of that. Well, I would push
back a little bit. I think something is
necessary when you have an SJC that is
12 to 12 on a case.
The book isn't helpful if an SJC is 12
to 12 on a decision.
uh something
I find that I found that to be very
uncomfortable and um think that
something could fix that. The where was
the where was was that your pin uh David
that that developed that consideration
of how to look at changes? That's my my
reflection on a very brilliant person
that uh I'm not foot footning right now.
Okay. Yeah, fair enough. Um, what I
appreciate about the conversation is
that it seems like the concern for
justice is shared by everyone and the
concern that the courts are faithfully
used for the care of its people shared
by everyone. everyone, we we all agree
on that. And I think what hopefully
people here are hearing is um a shared
concern across the board, uh that we are
faithful in what God's called us to do
and and yet trying to figure out how do
you do that because life is messy and
cases, particularly cases that go up to
SJC, are going to give you a way to
show, yeah, this is messy and and hard
to work out. Um for the sake of time,
I'm going to I'm going to move us on to
overture one. Uh no, no, no. That's what
we were just talking about. I'm gonna
move us on to overture 22. Now, if you
ever see an overture from the Pacific
Northwest, I I'm not personally
guaranteeing. I'm not saying I know
firsthand, but but I I'll just say
there's a significant correlation uh
between uh overtures from Pacific
Northwest and uh Howie Dano uh who uh
has had a hand often in these or uh has
contributed in some way. So, Howie, for
overture 22, Pacific Northwest uh
BCO20-3
on on regular standing, um c can you
tell us uh on on that overture? Um now,
there was agreement here. So, everyone
uh affirmed uh that in your respective
guides, but you just uh wanted to give
you a chance to kind of speak to it.
Well, it it was precipitated by an SJC
decision on a case that arose in my
presetary. Um, I didn't speak because
you're disqualified when it's free or
presbyterary. Um, it seemed there were I
mean there were some desending judges.
There were some concurring judges that
said uh we feel that the BCO constrains
us to vote this way, but we'd like to
see the change. Um
uh and it's my understanding that
there's a lot of churches that have
minimum voting ages and they're in kind
of an awkward position. They're not sure
what to do. Um
I think when an SJC decision comes down,
you you heat it. But uh
anyway, a lot of people maybe didn't
even know the case came out.
Nonetheless,
um, a good bit of, uh, so following Dr.
Coffin's
recommendation that you better put some
rationale in this thing,
we put some rationale in this thing. Uh,
touching how he's never how he's never
been afraid of footnotes uh, or
rationale in anything he's ever written.
Well, a lot of the footnotes come from
Dr. Boserman, who did a lot of
historical research. Uh I'm not as much
a footnote guy, but um so we just think
it makes biblical sense, it makes common
sense. It um makes historical sense and
and what Boserman has written couple I
think it just part of it got posted on
preced
summary of it. I just think it makes
makes sense. Now, in discussions with
other brothers, they have concerns that
um
I guess I can summarize, they're
concerned that if this passes,
it will encourage sessions to
admit children to the Lord's supper
at a premature age. They're more likely,
if this passes, to to do that uh bad
thing. Um, and that's why, you know,
working with Fred, he came up with
overture
33 and my position is if if overture 33
helps this to become more palatable, I'm
happy to endorse it. So,
okay. Uh, before we'll move to overture
33 next because I I think there's some
connection there. Um but I just want to
make sure that uh before we do um
overure 22 any further thoughts from uh
yeah let me let me I mean it focuses it
focuses it focuses on a phrase good and
regular standing and I think the SJC
decision treated that as if good and
regular standing refer to the same thing
and Bosserman's research points out that
good standing is not under censure
regular standing is something else so
for example in the history of American
Presbyterian regular standing routinely
meant a certain age. It actually meant
financial contributions, stuff like
that. So, regular standing was a
different animal than good standing. So,
that's a word. Now, minimum voting age
is kind of a subset of regular standing.
That's how
Anyway,
thanks Howie. Yep.
David or Fred, anything further to add?
I'll just note uh I did some quick math.
Uh Howie, I I want this to go into the
record of our our discussion. This third
discussion uh this overture uh number 22
has 24 lines of the actual overture.
Then it has 661 lines of rationale. So
that's a pretty significant ratio. Uh 24
lines is the actual overture. uh 661
lines uh to because you know since David
Coffin encouraged you to show some
rationale, you thought I I better show
more than just a little. That's why
we're that's why we're confident, your
honor, that the jury will vote in our
favor.
I I encourage everyone who's watching to
read uh even though it may be hard, read
all of it. Uh and hopefully it's it's
helpful to you. Um okay, so overture 33.
Now mo most of the overtures that uh
we've described and I qualified
intentionally in in the opening that
that it's typical or common for
overtures to come from prespitaries. Uh
I I think this is the only overture uh
that comes from the uh TE Fred Greco uh
overture 33. And so I think it's only
fair to let Fred kind of set the table.
This would be an overture addressing um
exams uh the the questions um from BCO
57. So Fred uh thoughts? So So the this
came this comes from me because it was
narrowly defeated in my presbyter.
The main argument against it was we
already do this so we don't need this.
Um I drafted this overture initially
after discussions with Howie. Um he as
he will often do actually we all do
this. We share overtures in advance to
try to come up with the best version
even before it comes to assembly. So I I
saw overture 22. I don't know when did
you start drafting? Like in September or
something like that. It was a long time
ago. And my comment to Howie was
I don't see this passing twothirds of
presbyteries unless something is done
here about the young communion issue.
And how's raised that point in other
context. Overtures in order to become
amendments to the book need to not only
pass assembly but they need to pass
twothirds of presbyaries.
And so I said, you know, for me, for
example, I would want to see this
addressed, this concern, and I think it
would help over to 22. Hence, you see in
our guides how he's saying yes on 33 of
22 passes and me saying yes on 22 of 33
passes. They're kind of companions. And
it's a I think it's a good uh exercise
and compromise uh that, you know, we've
come about working on this together. So,
you'll also be interested to know that
this is the short version of it. The
long version of it came from David
Coffin, and it was like a paragraph
long. And David's long version was
better than my short version, but using
the principle that the more words in an
overture, the less likely it is to pass,
I went with the short version. Um and
and and basically um my thought here is
sessions they should be doing this
because being admitted to the Lord's
table is not just about whether
someone's a Christian or not. Sometimes
people think that if a session doesn't
admit someone to the table, they're
saying they're not a Christian. That's
not what sessions are saying. under 1
Corinthians 11 they have to not only
make a profession of Christ but they
need to also say that they understand
discerning the Lord's body that is the
supper and the church hence the
categories that I put in this language
now uh against my presbyter that said
well we all already know this and are
doing this my thought is number one I'm
not sure everybody's doing this but
number two our book of church order is
not just a set of rules for courts to
follow. It's an affirmative statement of
our practice of Presbyterian polity. And
the average layman probably doesn't know
what's involved in the interview of a
young person. And so it certainly can't
hurt so that they know. They're not
going to be asked if they're super
inflapsarian. They're not going to be
asked whether they're covenantal or
dispensationalist. They're going to be
asked, can they get profession of faith?
Do they understand the supper? and do
they understand what it means to be a
member of a church? That's it. And so I
think this would be very helpful. Um and
while I understand overture 22 because
I've had lots of conversations with
Howie that over overture 22 is not
designed to sneak young child communion
in. And while I understand there are
many churches that do this, I also
understand that it has been a practice
by some churches in the PCA to admit
very young children using quote unquote
age appropriate confessions that consist
of something like Jesus loves me, not
showing any understanding of the supper
or of the church. And so to me that goes
against our historical polity and I
think what virtually everyone would say
is wise. So while this probably comes
under the category of doesn't absolutely
have to be in the book, I think it's
helpful and I think it also will have
the acedent uh benefit of helping
overure 22.
One thing to clarify Joel I don't maybe
I misheard you earlier the over Fred's
overture doesn't propose questions
if I read it right. It proposes
conclusions that the session must reach.
Yeah, that's correct. Yeah, thanks for
clarifying, Howie. You're right.
Now, they can ask those questions
however they want and they should assume
that they're going to get age
appropriate answers to them, right? But,
um, yeah, I I specifically try, Joel,
not to go into a lot of detail saying
you have to ask question one and two and
three, you know, because anyone who's
ever done a membership interview
understands it's a process and you have
to go back and forth and you we didn't
want to I didn't want to bind sessions.
I just wanted to give them categories.
As someone who regularly does member
interviews, let me say thanks uh Fred as
someone who the session and does this
with our elders. Let me say thank you.
Appreciate that.
But I I do think it's important uh what
Fred has offered and I think it it's
important for the session
the the way uh I have thought about this
is with um categories of maturity. The
child has to have intellectual maturity
enough to make a credible believable
profession of faith. He has to have
emotional maturity. That is to say, uh
he
is in some way or another um
uh
capable of selfmastery
with respect to participating in a right
that he hasn't just gone through the
motions. So it's not only understanding
the table but the capacity to take part
in a ceremony
um maturely and then finally spiritual
maturity that you see in the child uh
some sense of uh the wound that
woundedness of sin and uh the joy of
redemption. Uh
those three things seem to me to be
critical for a session and I I would
hope that what Fred has done will be
passed and we'll lead sessions to
contemplate things like that.
Two more things real quick based on what
David just said and I think this is one
way to summarize it is you must have the
requisite maturity to do both of those
things. They just don't usually happen
at the same age.
But our book now constitutionally
mandates at least for the SJC decision
that they occur at the same age. So um
and you're suggesting by passing both
these overtures that that uh allow that
it's basically stating now uh through
the BCO um how to navigate or balance
those two things.
Yeah, I think it demonstrates that you
must have the requisite maturity to do
each of those things, but it no longer
has to occur at the same age. And the
other reason I'm in favor of these, I
think there's something beautiful about
um Fred and I negotiating a compromise
and showing how this can I feel like
it's Reagan and Chip O'Neal or
something. I don't know. Let's
let's let this conversation go wide so
that people hear some of the work that
goes on. Um again with trust with
believing others intentions and what
they're trying to do and then operating
uh you know thinking the best and saying
okay right here's here's how uh this
could be improved upon or here's how
this would fit. Um thank you both thanks
for your work on on overture 22 and 33.
Um I think we've come to the end of uh
what what some of the set overtures that
we wanted to talk about again in the
context of quite a bit of an agreement
uh among the group and hearing some of
the areas where uh their different
thoughts. Um I'm going to just open it
up. Are are there any additional uh
overtures that or comments on overtures
that you think would be helpful before
we close?
Um, I don't have a lot of
thoughts on adding our committee on
Christian nationalism. Maybe maybe the
other guys do.
I'm I'm I'm just kind of ambivalent, I
guess.
Yeah, I think in my document I'm
recommending the letter because I think
that's an easier, cheaper way to do it.
Uh, using the the information that we
already have. I'm not sure that's
something we need to study to have a
full-blown study paper on, but I do
think it might satisfy some of the
brothers in various areas of the country
where it's a bigger concern to have a
couple of page document to hand to
congregant. I don't think it's
essential. I'd rather see us do that
than than do a full-blown study
committee. So you're you're talking
about Tennessee Valley 48 and remind me
does that propose authorize MBM to draft
it or write something and propose it to
the next GA? My guess my guess is it's
it's like the overture that appointed a
I appointed a commission to write the
letter on transgender minor proceed
procedures. But this would not be a
commission. It would be a committee. The
committee would bring it back to the
53rd assembly for approval. is my
understanding. So would they bring it
back for approval and amendments from
the floor? Presumably they would
presumably the first thing they would
say is we move that this be considered
without debate. Right. Dave Coffin used
to do all the time. I love it. Yeah. I
mean I don't know. My guess is that it
would actually come and it would be
assigned by the clerk to the appropriate
committee which would probably be the
overtures committee. And so it could be
amended in overtures but then couldn't
be amended on the floor. That would be
that would be my understanding at this
point. Well, that should be put in this
year's overure about how it gets back to
the floor because otherwise it wouldn't
be it wouldn't naturally go to the over
committee because it's not an overture.
But
um
report directly
right now. Yeah, that's true. That's
true.
Is this an ad committee? If it's not a
study committee.
Well, yeah. Any any adum Yeah. All
right. Um I'd hate to see the floor
be committee of the whole on nouns and
verbs. Yeah. Can we just say that it
seems like there's a broad concern about
Christian nationalism within the
boundaries of the PCA affecting members
uh attenders at churches or at least
you're seeing that from Arizona, from
South Texas, from Great Lakes, which is
right. These are different these aren't
all the same pocket. They're different
parts of the country expressing some
concern that the PCA weigh in on this. I
I'll just say whatever that weighing in
whether it is uh restating some of the
work that's been done historically or by
our own denomination whether that's
developing group of historians or men to
think through um how to uh address this
now it's it's being it's rising up it
seems like from different pockets not
just from the same spot. Well I I just
will repeat what I've said over and over
again. Um,
I haven't seen study committees except
in very rare circumstances do anything
useful permanently and often they do
harm because they end up dividing having
a majority minority report and then
nobody knows what we're what we're about
on it. I I think that uh we have
scholars and we have ministers and we
have all kinds of people who can write
useful things to help people understand
and we don't need to have the church
doing it and I I don't think we need to
have the church doing it on this. Um, I
mean, think how many t anybody hand out
the Freemasonry study report recently?
I mean,
well, there you have it.
All right.
Um, any other comments? So that that
touches on a number of the I think we've
covered quite a bit of ground, but I
don't want to cut off if if there are
comments or reflections on anything
else. No. Okay. Hey brothers, let me
just say thank you so much uh for
joining us um at AMR. Hope is that uh we
can work toward both the unity and
faithfulness of the PCA and and doing
that through conversations like this. Uh
thanks for watching. Uh thanks for
following the links to go and read and
prepare. Uh our hope is that you have an
extra resource here uh to get ready for
the 52nd General Assembly and we'll look
forward to seeing you in Chattanooga.
Amen. Take care.